<chapter id="docmgmt">
  <title>Document management</title>
  
  <para>The document management support of jBPM is based on 
    <ulink url="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=170">Java Content Repository</ulink>.
    That is a standard java specification for integrating document management
    systems into Java.  The basic idea is as follows: 
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>In the jBPM configuration, one or more JCR repository services are configured</listitem>
    <listitem>Next, JCR Node's can be stored in the process variables</listitem>
    <listitem>Upon retrieval, the stored information will result in a lookup of the node in the repository</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>That way, a multiversioned document can be stored one process variable.
  </para>
  
  <para>The typical use case for this feature is a document approval process.  A document 
    needs to be approved and updated.  That document (e.g. a word document), can be 
    stored in a JCR-content-repository-node.  The node contains all the versions of the 
    document.  So that later in the process, people still can consult the historical 
    versions of the document.
  </para>
  
  <para><emphasis role="bold">IMPORTANT NOTE:</emphasis> The name of the jbpm context service 
    MUST correspond with the name of the repository (repository.getDescriptor(Repository.REP_NAME_DESC)).
    This is to make the match between the reference stored in the jbpm process variables and 
    the repository when a node-variable is being loaded from the jBPM DB.
  </para>

  <section id="repositorylookupinjndi">
    <title>Repository lookup in JNDI</title>
  </section>

  <section id="Jackrabbit">
    <title>Jackrabbit</title>
    <para>see also http://jackrabbit.apache.org/
    </para>
    <para>Deploying jackrabbit.  library requirements.  jboss deployment issue 
      with commons-collections-3.1.
    </para>
    <para>configuring the jbpm jackrabbit service.
    </para>
    <para>configuring jackrabbit.  see http://jackrabbit.apache.org/doc/config.html
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="Multiple workspaces">
    <title>Multiple workspaces</title>
  </section>

</chapter>
