<chapter id="getstarted">

  <title id="getstarted.title">Getting started</title>
  
  <section id="getstarted.jbpmbpel">

    <title>Getting JBoss jBPM BPEL</title>
    
    <para>The releases of the jBPM BPEL extension can be found in the 
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/products/jbpm/downloads">jBPM download page</ulink>. The 
      package JBoss jBPM BPEL contains the jBPM BPEL software (sources and binaries) plus the 
      thirdparty libraries it depends on.</para>
      
    <para>The BPEL extension is based on jBPM 3. Downloading the jBPM distribution separately is
      strongly recommended but strictly optional, as the BPEL package already contains the required
      jBPM binaries.</para>
      
    <para>Once you download the package, unzip it to a suitable location in your machine.
      It should all unzip into a single directory named <literal>jbpm-bpel-&lt;version&gt;</literal>.
      Make sure you don't use a directory which has any spaces in the path (such as
      the <literal>Program Files</literal> directory on Windows) as this may cause problems.</para>
      
    <para>Alternatively, you can get the software from CVS with the following parameters.
      Once you have access, look for module <literal>jbpm.bpel</literal>.</para>
      
    <table>
    
      <title>CVS parameters</title>
      
      <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>

        <thead>
        
          <row>
            <entry>Parameter</entry>
            <entry>Value</entry>
          </row>

        </thead>
        
        <tbody>

          <row>
            <entry>Connection type</entry>
            <entry>pserver</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>User</entry>
            <entry>anonymous</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Password</entry>
            <entry>(when prompted for a password, just press enter)</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Host</entry>
            <entry>anoncvs.forge.jboss.com</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Port</entry>
            <entry>2401 (the default)</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Repository path</entry>
            <entry>/cvsroot/jbpm</entry>
          </row>
        
        </tbody>
      
      </tgroup>
      
    </table>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="getstarted.jbossas">
  
    <title>Getting JBoss Application Server</title>
  
    <para>The jBPM BPEL software builds on J2EE 1.4 APIs and a number of open source projects. 
      While it is not tied to JBoss AS, the guide provides deployment instructions for JBoss AS 
      only. Even if you use a different application server in production, we still encourage you
      to try this software in development along with JBoss AS. If you like it and decide to take
      it to production, we can help you through the <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/kjru7">forum
      </ulink> or our <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/services/index">support services</ulink>.
      </para>
      
    <para>For instructions on getting JBoss AS, see <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/kl9wl">
      Downloading and Installing JBoss</ulink>.</para>
    
    <note><para>Please make sure you select a JBoss AS version and server profile compatible with
      J2EE 1.4. Specifically, jBPM BPEL has been tested with versions 4.0.3SP1 and 4.0.4.GA in the
      <literal>default</literal> profile.</para></note>
      
  </section>
   
  <section id="getstarted.ant">
   
    <title>Getting Apache Ant</title>
       
    <para>Ant scripts dramatically simplify the development and deployment of BPEL proceses.
      The tutorial chapter assumes you have installed Ant and are able to execute targets. 
      Furthermore, you need Ant to build the jBPM BPEL service archive.</para>
      
    <para>For directions on getting Ant, see <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org/manual/install.html">
      Installing Ant</ulink>.</para>
    
    <note><para>In order to run <literal>junit</literal> tasks, Ant requires the JUnit library.
      You will find this library in the <literal>lib/junit</literal> directory of the jBPM BPEL
      distribution. Remember to copy it to Ant's <literal>lib</literal> directory.</para></note>
   
  </section>
  
  <section id="getstarted.eclipse">
  
    <title>Getting the Eclipse BPEL designer</title>
    
    <para>The Eclipse community has begun a <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/bpel/">BPEL
      project</ulink>. The goal of this project is "to add comprehensive support to 
      Eclipse for the definition, authoring, editing, deploying, testing and debugging of 
      WS-BPEL 2.0 processes".</para>
      
    <para>The JBoss jBPM team has been in touch with the comitters of this project. Expect
      tighter integration between the Eclipse Designer and jBPM BPEL shortly after key pieces
      of functionality such as Runtime Framework and Debug become available.</para>
      
    <para>You do not have to wait, tough. You can get started with the Eclipse BPEL designer
      and jBPM BPEL <emphasis role="bold">today</emphasis>! Please visit our <ulink 
      url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JbpmBpelDesigner">Wiki</ulink> knowledge
      base for a Quick Start guide.</para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section id="getstarted.setup">
  
    <title>Service setup</title>

    <para>The jBPM BPEL service archive (<literal>.sar</literal>) contains the libraries and 
      configuration files required to execute BPEL processes. The following sections describe
      how to configure, package and deploy the jBPM BPEL service to JBoss AS.</para>
      
    <section id="getstarted.setup.config">
      
      <title>Service configuration</title>
      
      <para>The configuration files reside in <literal>src/resources/jbpm-bpel.sar</literal>.
        These files provide settings to Hibernate and to jBPM itself.</para>
    
      <section id="getstarted.setup.config.hibernate">
      
        <title>Hibernate configuration</title>
        
        <para>Starting from version 1.0 alpha 3, the BPEL extension incorporates the jBPM
          persistence model, described in the chapter on <ulink 
          url="http://docs.jboss.com/jbpm/v3/userguide/persistence.html">persistence</ulink> of 
          the jBPM user guide. jBPM uses Hibernate as its object-relational mapper.
          The next table describes the Hibernate configuration files.</para>
          
        <table>
        
          <title>Hibernate configuration files</title>
      
          <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
          
            <thead>
        
              <row>
                <entry>File</entry>
                <entry>Notes</entry>
              </row>
              
              </thead>
              
            <tbody>
              
              <row>
                <entry><literal>hibernate.properties</literal></entry>
                <entry><para>Contains database connection properties and miscellaneus values. 
                  Since the service runs inside the application server, you should configure 
                  Hibernate to obtain connections from a data source registered in JNDI.</para>
                  <para>Refer to the <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/e4mp3">Configuration</ulink>
                  chapter of the Hibernate manual for instructions.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><literal>ehcache.xml</literal></entry>
                <entry><para>Supplies parameters for the default second-level cache provider.</para>
                  <para>The chapter on <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/pv6w9">Performance</ulink> in
                  the Hibernate manual describes the use of caches to improve performance.</para>
                  </entry>
              </row>
              
            </tbody>
            
          </tgroup>
          
        </table>
        
        <para>Apart from the above files, jBPM BPEL service includes a data source deployment 
          descriptor: <literal>jbpm-bpel-ds.xml</literal>. In addition to the preconfigured data
          source, this file also describes a <literal>HypersonicDatabase</literal> MBean. Upon
          deployment, this MBean creates a database in the same VM the server is running. This
          database is written to disk when the server shuts down, but no other process has access
          to it.</para>
          
        <para>Administrators often prefer to separate data sources from services and applications.
          The data source described in the previous paragraph is intended for evaluation and 
          development purposes. It should not be regarded as a production arrangement.</para>
          
      </section>
      
      <section id="getstarted.setup.config.jbpm">
      
        <title>jBPM settings</title>

        <para>The file <literal>jbpm.cfg.xml</literal> contains the jBPM configuration. The 
          following table summarizes the relevant information items in the context of BPEL.</para>

        <table>
        
          <title>Relevant jBPM information items for BPEL</title>
        
          <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        
          <thead>
        
            <row>
              <entry>Setting</entry>
              <entry>Notes</entry>
            </row>
          
          </thead>
          
          <tbody>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>&lt;jbpm-context&gt;</literal></entry>
              <entry>Configures the jBPM context with a set of services. The persistence
                and relation services are mandatory; other services may be disabled at will.</entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry><literal>&lt;string name="resource.hibernate.cfg.xml"&gt;</literal></entry>
              <entry>References an alternate XML resource listing the Hibernate mapping files.
                </entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry><literal>&lt;string name="resource.hibernate.properties"&gt;</literal></entry>
              <entry>References an alternate properties resource containing the JDBC connection 
                parameters.</entry>
            </row>
          
          </tbody>
          
          </tgroup>
          
        </table>
        
      </section>
      
    </section>
      
    <section id="getstarted.setup.pack">
    
      <title>Packaging</title>
      
      <para>Once you have set the configuration, building the service archive is easy.
        Copy or rename file <literal>ant.example.properties</literal> in your jBPM BPEL 
        base directory to <literal>ant.properties</literal>. Edit the values therein to
        match the directory where you installed JBoss AS and your preferred server configuration.
        </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[# JBoss AS installation directory
jboss.home=/jboss/home
# JBoss server configuration
jboss.server=default

# jBPM library versions
jbpm.version=3.1.2
jbpm.bpel.version=1.1.Beta2]]></programlisting>

      <para>To build the service archive, locate <literal>build.xml</literal> in the base
        directory and run the target that corresponds to your JBoss AS version.</para>

      <table>
      
        <title>Ant targets for building the service archive</title>
        
        <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      
          <thead>
          
            <row>
              <entry>Target</entry>
              <entry>Version</entry>
            </row>
        
          </thead>
          
          <tbody>
        
            <row>
              <entry><literal>build.service.402</literal></entry>
              <entry>4.0.2</entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry><literal>build.service.403</literal></entry>
              <entry>4.0.3 SP1</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>build.service.404</literal></entry>
              <entry>4.0.4 GA</entry>
            </row>
        
          </tbody>
        
        </tgroup>
        
      </table>

      <para>If all goes well you should see messages much like the following:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[build.service.404:
      [jar] Building jar: .../jbpm-bpel.sar]]></screen>
      
      <para>JBoss AS 4.0.4 and later versions ship with the new web services stack,
        <emphasis>JBossWS</emphasis>. Like its predecessor in earlier JBoss AS versions, this
        stack implements the Web Services for J2EE specification, version 1.1. However, some
        idiosyncrasies of the Axis-based stack result in slight incompatibilities with the new
        implementation. Specifically, a number of SAAJ methods do not behave as expected. 
        JBossWS exhibits results that match the reference implementation.</para>
        
      <para>Starting from version 1.1.Beta2, jBPM BPEL has been revised to work with both stacks.
        The workarounds used to maintain compatibility with the old stack might fail when parsing
        or formatting certain SOAP envelopes. If you encounter a SOAP-related problem, please try 
        upgrading to JBoss AS 4.0.4 or later to determine whether the old stack is causing the
        problem. Should the issue remain, let us know via the <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/kjru7">
        forum</ulink>.</para>

    </section>
      
    <section id="getstarted.setup.deploy">
    
      <title>Deployment</title>
      
      <para>Before deploying the service, start JBoss in the server configuration of your choice
        (see <ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/rjqkb">Server Configurations</ulink>). Afterwards,
        run the <literal>deploy-service</literal> target of <literal>build.xml</literal> in the
        jBPM BPEL installation directory.</para>
        
      <para>The following log entries confirm the deployment of the jBPM BPEL data source, service
        and web application, respectively.</para>
  
      <screen><![CDATA[00:39:45,390 INFO  [ConnectionFactoryBindingService] Bound ConnectionManager 'jboss.jca:name=jbpmBpelDS,service=DataSourceBinding' to JNDI name 'java:jbpmBpelDS'
00:39:45,406 INFO  [JbpmConfiguration] using jbpm configuration resource 'jbpm.cfg.xml'
00:39:45,437 INFO  [TomcatDeployer] deploy, ctxPath=/jbpm-bpel, warUrl=.../tmp/deploy/tmp30743jbpm-bpel-exp.war/]]></screen>  

      <para>JBoss is now ready to deploy process definitions and BPEL-powered web services.</para>
      
    </section>
    
  </section>

</chapter>