<chapter id="tutorial">

  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <para>The best way to get acquainted with BPEL is to see it in action. For this reason,
    we included some examples that will help you get started quickly. At
    this point, you should have the jBPM BPEL service running inside JBoss. If you
    do not, please read the <link linkend="getstarted" endterm="getstarted.title"/>
    chapter first.</para>
    
  <para>In this chapter we will guide you through the example setup procedure. The next two 
    chapters contain the actual examples.</para>
    
  <section id="tutorial.setup.jwsdp">

    <title>Getting the Java Web Services Development Pack</title>
    
    <para>jBPM BPEL relies on the Web Services for J2EE (WSEE) model for exposing the 
      functionality a BPEL process delivers. Some of the server artifacts required for a WSEE 
      deployment can be automatically generated from WSDL documents.</para>
      
    <para>Starting from JBoss AS 4.0.4, the web services implementation features a
      toolkit called <literal>wstools</literal>. If you are using that version of JBoss AS, no
      further action is required in this section.</para>
      
    <para>For earlier JBoss AS versions, JBoss recommended the <literal>wscompile</literal> 
      tool from the Java Web Services Development Pack. Please refer to the <ulink 
      url="http://java.sun.com/webservices/jwsdp/index.jsp">Java WSDP</ulink> site for download
      and installation instructions.</para>
  
  </section>
    
  <section id="tutorial.setup.environment">
  
    <title>Defining the environment</title>
    
    <para>The resources related to each sample process reside in a separate subdirectory 
       under <literal>doc/examples</literal>. Each subdirectory contains an Ant script to assist
       in carrying out process deployment tasks.</para>
       
    <para>Note that the individual scripts import a template located in the <literal>common
      </literal> subdirectory. If you organize your resources in the same way as the examples,
      you can take advantage of this template in your own project.</para>
      
    <para>Each runtime environment is likely to be different from all others. For this
      reason, the build template needs to be made aware of your particular environment.
      Copy or rename file <literal>ant.example.properties</literal> in the <literal>doc/examples
      </literal> subdirectory to <literal>ant.properties</literal>. Edit the values there to 
      match your jBPM BPEL and JWSDP installation directories. The new values are shared
      among all examples.</para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[# jBPM BPEL installation directory 
jbpm.bpel.home=/jbpm/bpel/home

# JWSDP installation directory
# optional for JBoss 4.0.4+
# required for JBoss 4.0.3-
!jwsdp.home=/jwsdp/home]]></programlisting>

    <para>Controlling multiple processes at once becomes as easy as controlling a single
      process with the build file located in <literal>doc/examples</literal>. This script 
      leverages the <literal>subant</literal> task for running build targets on a collection 
      of projects.</para>
  
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial.setup.dbschema">
  
    <title>Creating the database schema</title>
    
    <para>Starting with version 1.0 alpha 4, a web application deployed along the jBPM BPEL
      service executes administrative requests such as creating the database schema and
      deploying a process definition.</para>      
    
    <para>Before you deploy process definitions to the database, the jBPM schema must exist in
      the database. The schema creation can be manual or automatic, at your choice.</para>
      
    <para>Automatic schema creation is convenient for evaluation and development purposes.
      This is why it is the default setting. To disable it, remove the <literal>
      hibernate.hbm2ddl.auto</literal> property from <literal>hibernate.properties</literal> in 
      <literal>src/resources/jbpm-bpel.sar</literal> and redeploy the jBPM BPEL service.
    </para>
    
    <para>When you turn off automatic schema creation, you need a way to create it manually. 
      The global process deployment script provides some targets for posting administrative 
      schema requests to the jBPM BPEL web application: <literal>create-schema</literal> and 
      <literal>drop-schema</literal>.</para>
      
    <para>Hibernate will emit a few log messages to the server console when the schema gets
      created either way. The output below corresponds to manual creation.</para>
      
    <screen><![CDATA[22:45:00,796 INFO  [SchemaExport] Running hbm2ddl schema export
22:45:00,812 INFO  [SchemaExport] exporting generated schema to database
22:45:00,828 INFO  [DatasourceConnectionProvider] Using datasource: java:/jbpmBpelDS
22:45:00,921 INFO  [SchemaExport] schema export complete]]></screen>
  
  </section>
    
  <section id="tutorial.setup.xmlapis">
  
    <title>Replacing the default implementation of the XML APIs</title>
    
    <para>There are known issues with the implementations of the XML APIs in Java SE 1.4.2 and 
      1.5.0. The solution is to employ the Endorsed Standards Override Mechanism for replacing
      these implementations with more recent versions of Apache Xalan and Apache Xerces.</para>
      
    <para>You will find adequate replacement libraries in the <literal>lib/endorsed</literal> 
      subdirectory of JBoss AS. Please follow the instructions for deploying endorsed standards
      classes in the Java SE <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/guide/standards/">
      Guide to Features</ulink>.</para>

  </section>

</chapter>